A Guide to the Whittington W. Clement Papers, 1988-2001
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Papers, 1988-2001
Library of Virginia
38721
3 cubic feet
Whittington W. Clement
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Whittington W. Clement, 16 November 2001.
Biographical Information
Whittington "Whitt" W. Clement was born in Danville, Virginia on 15 November 1947. He attended Danville's public schools and graduated from Episcopal High School in Alexandria, Virginia. He received his bachelor of arts and law degree from the University of Virginia. In 1987, he was elected as a Democrat to represent the 20th House District, including Danville and part of Pittsylvania County, in the Virginia House of Delegates. During his fourteen years in the House of Delegates (1988-2001), Clement served on the Transportation, Appropriations, and Science and Technology Committees. In 2001, he ran for Attorney General in the Democratic primary, but was defeated. He is currently serving as Secretary of Transportation in the administration of Governor Mark Warner and chairman of the Commonwealth Transportation Board.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1988-2001, of Whittington "Whitt" W. Clement, former member of the Virginia House of Delegates, consisting of legislative files from his service as a delegate from the 20th House District, encompassing Danville and parts of Pittsylvania County.
The files cover a variety of topics such as banking, consumer issues, crime, education, the environment, gun control, judicial selection, medical and health issues, public safety, taxation, and transportation. These files also include commending and memorial resolutions, and material relating to budget amendments. The files include copies of house and senate bills and resolutions, notes, memorandums, correspondence, resolutions, newsclippings, press releases, financial impact statements, reports, and studies. Of note are Clement's legislative efforts for Danville and surrounding area, including the Danville city charter, redevelopment, Lake Gaston pipeline, tax exemptions for area non-profit organizations, and resolutions supporting the A. L. Philpott Southside Economic Development Commission. The collection includes files for every year Clement served in the House of Delegates except 1992. Also, there is only one file for 1993.
Arrangement
Arrangement
The folders are arranged alphabetically within each series.
Organization
Organized into the following fourteen series: I. 1988 Legislation; II. 1989 Legislation; III. 1990 Legislation; IV. 1991 Legislation; V. 1993 Legislation; VI. 1994 Legislation; VII. 1994 Special Session - Parole, etc.; VIII. 1995 Legislation; IX. 1996 Legislation; X. 1997 Legislation; XI. 1998 Legislation; XII. 1999 Legislation; XIII. 2000 Legislation; XIV. 2001 Legislation.
Contents List
- 1988 Legislation, 16 folders (Box 1)
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Appeals (HB 627) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Auxiliary Policeman (HB 815) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clement Legislation (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Danville (HJR 23) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Danville Charter (HB 57) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Division of Trusts (HB 269) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dropouts (HJR 47) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Drug Abuse (HB 174) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Election of City Council (HB 626) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - God's Storehouse (HB 135) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - HJR/SJR, Studies for (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - James Motley (HJR 16) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Militia and Police (HB 173) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Power of Attorney (HB 570) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - School Administrators Teaching (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Tax Exemptions (HB 817) (Box 1, Folder 16)
- 1989 Legislation, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Annoying Telephone Calls (HB 1340) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Higher Education Data, 1988-1989 (HJR 46) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Historic Landmarks Reorganization (HB 1748) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Mass Transit Fund - Annexation (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Termination of Trusts (HB 1342) (Box 1, Folder 21)
- 1990 Legislation, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Certificates of Full Satisfaction; Release of Deeds of Trust (HB 310) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Danville City Charter (HB 42) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Division of Trusts (HB 185) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "Fiduciary," Definition of (HB 187) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Juvenile and Domestic Courts Medical Reports or Evidence (HB 486) (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - TVA Distribution (HB 604) (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - "Virginia Disclaimer Statutes" (HB 184) (Box 1, Folder 28)
- 1991 Legislation, 8 folders (Box 1-2)
  - Danville City Charter Amendment (HB 1204) (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Downtown Properties Resolution (HJR 417) (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Governor's Highway - Environment (HB 1575) (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Gun Control (HB 1989) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Guns on School Property (HB 1574) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Literacy and Probation Resolution (HJR 317) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Rail Passenger Project Funding Study (HJR 471) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - State Board of Health (HB 1577) (Box 2, Folder 5)
- 1993 Legislation, 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Vines - Carper Judgeship (Box 2, Folder 6)
- 1994 Legislation, 15 folders (Box 2)
  - Assignment under Virginia Retirement System (HB 310) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Clement Legislation (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Collection of Fines Study (HJR 207) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Confederate Cemeteries (HB 701) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Delinquency of a Minor (HB 829) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Delinquent Tax Sale (HB 1204) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Goodyear Resolution (HJR 62) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Southside Virginia Marketing Council (HB 340) (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Spot Blight (HB 1205) (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Taxation of Remainder Interest (HB 700) (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Unpaid Court Fines and Fees (HB 1208) (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - University of Virginia - Selection of Management of Financial Funds (HB 525) (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Vehicles on Sidewalk (HB 311) (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Weed Control (HB 1206) (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Work - Release Wages (HB 1207) (Box 2, Folder 21)
- 1994 Special Session - Parole, etc., 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Survey of Criminal Justice (Box 2, Folder 22)
- 1995 Legislation, 13 folders (Box 2)
  - Appointment of Guardians (HB 1886) (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Augmented Estate (HB 1724) (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Commending Resolutions and Memorials (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Environmental Assessment Privilege (HB 1845) and Voluntary Remediation (HB 1847) (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Involuntary Admission - Thumbprinting (HB 1885) (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Judicial Selection (HB 2387) (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Legislative Calendar (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Liability Insurance (HB 1686) (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Lottery to Localities (HB 1693) (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Nonresident Fiduciaries (HB 2127) (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Philpott Commission (HJR 451) (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Surety Bonds (HB 1740) (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Tax Exempt - Hughes Memorial Home Trust (HB 1477) (Box 2, Folder 35)
- 1996 Legislation, 18 folders (Box 2-3)
  - Bankers/Environment - underground storage tanks (HB 591) (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Charitable Gift Annuities (HB 897) (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Clement Legislation (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Deputy Sheriffs (HB 242) (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Duplicative Programs in Higher Education (HB 322) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Estimate Tax Returns (HB 369) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Firefighters/Rescue Squads (HJR 14) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Judicial Nomination Commission (HB 456) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Junior Livestock (HB 63) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Little Life Inc. (Family Life Services of Southern Virginia, Inc.) Real Estate Tax Exemption (HB 240) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Lottery (HB 663) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Organ Donors (HJR 100) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Out-Of-Basin Transfer of Water (Lake Gaston Pipeline) (HB 662) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Philpott Commission (HB 348) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Real Estate Agents (HB 898) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Sale/Deed of Trust (HB 368) (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Student Internship Programs (HB 507) (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Surplus Property (HB 899) (Box 3, Folder 14)
- 1997 Legislation, 20 folders (Box 3-4)
  - Bond Reduction (HB 2262) (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Budget Amendments - Compensation and Economic Development (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Budget Amendments - Elementary and Secondary Education (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Budget Amendments - Higher Education/Transportation (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Budget Amendments - Human Resources (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Budget Amendments - Legislation/Judicial/Executive Outlay (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Budget Amendments - Public Safety/Natural Resources (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Clement Legislation (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Danville City Charter - Danville Redevelopment and Housing Authority (HB 1821) (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Dental Hygienists (HJR 81) (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Enterprise Zones (HB 2031) (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Environmental Audits (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Judicial Nominations Commission (HB 2456) (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Junior Livestock - Non-profit Sales and Use Tax Exemptions (HB 1725) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Ratites (HB 2665) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Regional Juvenile Detention Commissions (HB 2046) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Roman Eagle Memorial Home - Real Estate Tax Exemption (HB 1822, 1850) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Shareholders (HB 2126) (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Trademarks (HB 2620) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Retirements System - Service Credit for Pregnancy Leave (HB 1958) (Box 4, Folder 7)
- 1998 Legislation, 39 folders (Box 4-5)
  - Abduction by Prisoners or Juveniles in Secure Facility (HB 289) (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Abuse of 911 Calls (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Appeal by Commonwealth (HB 290) (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Bond Insurance (HB 31) (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Budget Amendments (I-II) (Box 4, Folder 12-13)
  - Car Tax (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Clement Legislation (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Clippings (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Commending Resolutions (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Credit for Taxes Paid to Other States (HB 33) (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Danville Regional Health System - Exemption from Retail Sales Use Taxes (HB 293) (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Danville Regional Medical System - Real Estate Tax Exemption (HB 294) (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Delinquent Juveniles in Detention (HB 419) (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - DUI - Third Offense/Penalty (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Firearms Use or Display in Commission of a Felony/Penalty (HB 292) (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Goodwill - Retail Sales Use Tax Exemption (HB 35) (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Hospital Peer Review (HB 1391) (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Juvenile Offenders to Circuit Court (HB 420) (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Larceny/Penalty (HB 288) (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - License Plates for the Delivery of Unladen Vehicles (HB 418) (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Local Judicial Nominating Committee (HB 744) (I-II) (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Marijuana, Definition of (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Motor Vehicle Habitual Offender Penalty (HB 295) (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Motor Vehicle Sales Tax - Reduced by Trade In (HB 34) (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Offenses in Secure Juvenile Facilities, Penalty (HB 421) (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Payments from Other Localities for Children in Secure Detention Facilities (HB 888) (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Philpott Southside Economic Development Commission (HJR 108) (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Power of Attorney - Apparent Authority (HB 532) (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Protective Orders/Filing Petitions (HB 291) (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Punishment for Abusive Language (HB 1366) (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Southside Virginia Marketing Council (HB 556) (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Squire Armory - Military Affairs (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Uniform Principal and Income Act (HB 842) (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Uniform Prudent Investor Act (HB 841) (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Unfair Settlement Practices - Auto Glass (HB 417) (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Virginia Public Building Authority - Powers, duties, etc. (HB 449) (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Virginia Trademark (HB 264) (Box 5, Folder 18)
- 1999 Legislation, 16 folders (Box 5-6)
  - Ashworth, Wayne - Commending Resolution (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Burton, Irvin C., Sr. - Memorial Resolution (HJR 531) (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Certificate of Public Need (HB 2090) (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Clement Legislation (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Dan River High School Baseball Team - Commending Resolution (HJR 577) (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - HUBZone (Historically underutilized business zone) (HB 2747) (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Intervention/Schools (HB 1799) (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Judicial Selection (HB 2524) (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Masonite Corporation - Commending Resolution (HJR 534) (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Nurse Anesthetists (HB 2539) (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Photomonitoring of Traffic Light (HB 1798) (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Route 58 (HB 2100) (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Route 58 Revenue (HB 2088) (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Special License Plates - 82nd Airborne Division (HB 1797) (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Tobacco (HJR 581) (Box 6, Folder 5)
- 2000 Legislation, 16 folders (Box 6)
  - Budget Amendments - Capital Outlay (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Budget Amendments - Elementary and Secondary Education (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Budget Amendments - General (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Budget Amendments - Higher Education (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Budget Amendments - Natural Resources (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Budget Amendments - Non-state Agencies (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Budget Amendments - Public Safety (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Budget Amendments - Trade and Commerce (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Budget Amendments - Transportation (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Cigarette Enforcement Act (HB 1387) (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Commending Resolutions (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Episcopal High School-Woodberry Forest School - Commending Resolution (HJR 25) (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Fire Services - Revenue Bonds (HB 517) (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Review of the 2000 Session, by Todd Yeatts (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Route 29 Study (HJR 278) (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Uniform Statewide Building Code - Rehabilitation of Existing Buildings (HB 518) (Box 6, Folder 21)
- 2001 Legislation, 15 folders (Box 6-7)
  - Budget Amendments (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Fake ID's (HB 2449) (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Flipping (Mortgage Lending Practice) (HB 2708) (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Income Tax Revenue Sharing (HB 2446) (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Judicial Nominations Committee (HB 2445) (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Line of Duty Act (HB 2448) (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Motor Vehicle Sales and Use Tax (HB 2452) (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Museums - Virginia College Building Authority (HB 2707) (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - North Carolina Reciprocal Agreement (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Nursing Home Barriers (HB 2388) (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Police Custody (HB 2450) (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Prisoner Reimbursement (HB 2389) (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Privacy Bill (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - State Park Fees - Golden Passport Two cards (HB 2451) (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Uniform Information Transactions Act (UCITA) - Consumer Protection (HB 2387) (Box 7, Folder 13)